Hieu Anh Doan

Summary _

I am a research chemical engineer who specializes in using computation to aid materials development and discovery. My toolset includes high-throughput quantum mechanical simulations, chemical informatics, machine learning, and most importantly, fundamental physics and chemistry. I have extensive experience in managing multiple projects independently as well as collaboratively in multidisciplinary teams.

Skills_

Programming Python, C/C++, Java, Fortran, shell scripting
 Modeling VASP, Gaussian, Aspen, MATLAB, COMSOL
 Data Science R, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Numpy, Scipy

Experience ___

Postdoctoral Appointee

2018-present

ARGONNE NATIONAL LABORATORY - MATERIALS SCIENCE DIVISION

Lemont, IL

My current interest is in utilizing high-throughput Density Functional Theory simulations and active learning (e.g. Bayesian Optimization) for accelerated discovery of new functional materials relevant to energy storage and catalysis. Projects:

- Electrolyte design for sustainable redox flow batteries
- Catalyst stability optimization for biomass conversion
- Chemical reaction pathways prediction

Postdoctoral Fellow 2016-2018

NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY - INORGANOMETALLIC CATALYST DESIGN CENTER

Evanston, IL

My work focused on designing optimal catalysts for natural gas conversion by means of cheminformatics and molecular simulations:

- Evaluated the prospect of supported metal oxide nanoclusters for direct conversion of methane to methanol
- Performed high-throughput computational screening of metal-organic frameworks for efficient natural gas utilization
- Additional responsibilities: Mentor Ph.D. students, write proposals to acquire research funding and allocations at supercomputing centers.

Graduate Research Assistant

2010-2015

UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON

Houston, TX

I used a combination of quantum mechanical simulations and kinetic modeling to study catalysts and catalytic reactions:

- Developed a microkinetic modeling code for activity prediction of multifunctional catalytic materials
- Conducted a detailed mechanistic study of CO oxidation over gold/titania catalysts to explain experimental observations (published in *Science*)
- Performed computational screening to guide experimental evaluations of improved palladium catalysts for methane slip reduction in natural gas vehicles (funded by **Shell**)
- Other responsibilities: Train new group members, supervise undergraduate research projects, conduct tutoring sessions and grade assignments and exams for the following courses (20-30 students/class): Chemical Engineering Thermodynamics, Design, Safety&Reliability

EducationPh. D. in Chom

Ph.D. in Chemical Engineering

December 2015 Houston, TX

UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON

• Dissertation: Computational Screening of Bifunctional Catalysts for CO and CH₄ Oxidation

Advisor : Professor Lars C. Grabow

B.S. in Chemical Engineering - Magna Cum Laude

December 2009

UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON

Houston, TX

Ventura, CA

· Honor Thesis: Experimental Analysis of Soot Combustion in Diesel Particulate Filter

• Advisor : Professor Dan Luss

Honors & Awards _

2020	Best paper award from Joint Center of Energy Storage Research (JCESR)	Argonne, IL
2019	Best poster presentation at the Argonne Postdoctoral Symposium	Argonne, IL
2018	Best fundamental paper award from the American Institute of Chemical Engineers	Houston, TX
2015	Kokes travel award for the 24 th North American Catalysis Society Meeting	Pittsburgh, PA
2015	Invited for a special topic talk at the Gordon Research Conference	Ventura, CA
2007	Summer undergraduate research fellowship	Houston, TX

Selected Talks

Quantum Chemistry Informed Active Learning to Guide the Development and Discovery of Energy Storage Materials JCESR Webinar Argonne, IL

JCESR Webinar

Toward the Optimal Design of Molybdenum Carbide Catalysts for Biomass Conversion

Aug. 2019

(Invited)
AMERICAN CHEMICAL SOCIETY
San Diego, CA

Theoretical Insights into Selective Oxidation of Methane to Methanol on

Porphyrin-supported Copper Nanoclusters

Jun. 2017

NORTH AMERICAN CATALYSIS SOCIETY METTING

Denver, CO

Importance of the Material Gap in Complete Methane Oxidation over Pd Catalysts

Sep. 2015

AMERICAN INSTITUTE OF CHEMICAL ENGINEERS ANNUAL MEETING

Salt Lake, UT

The Critical Role of Water at the Gold-Titania Interface in Catalytic CO Oxidation Feb. 2015

Publications _

GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCE

- 1. H. Qian, M. J. Counihan, H. A. Doan, A. S. Danis, W. Setwipatanachai, N. S. Purwanto, J. Rodriguez-Lopez, R. S. Assary, J. S. Moore, "Mesolytic Cleavage of Homobenzylic Ethers for Programmable End-of-Life Function in Redoxmers." *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*. In review.
- 2. G. Agarwal, H. A. Doan, R. S. Assary, "Molecular Structure and Electron Affinity of Metal-Solvent Complexes: Insights from Density Functional Theory Simulations." *Journal of the Electrochemical Society* 167, 5636-5646, 2020.
- 3. H. A. Doan, G. Agarwal, H. Qian, M. J. Counihan, J. Rodriguez-Lopez, R. S. Assary, "Quantum Chemistry-Informed Active Learning to Accelerate the Design and Discovery of Sustainable Energy Storage Materials." *Chemistry of Materials* 32, 6338-6346, 2020.
- M. Zhou, H. A. Doan, L. A. Curtiss, R. S. Assary, "Effect of Ni Dopant on Furan Activation over Mo₂C Surface: Insights from First-Principles-Based Microkinetic Modeling." *Journal of Physical Chemistry C* 124, 5636-5646, 2020.
- 5. H. A. Doan, Z. Li, O. K. Farha, J. T. Hupp, R. Q. Snurr, "Theoretical Insights into Direct Conversion of Methane to Methanol over Supported Dicopper Oxo Nanoclusters." *Catalysis Today* 312, 2-9, 2018.

- 6. H. A. Doan, M. K. Sharma, W. S. Epling, L. C. Grabow, "From Active-Site Models to Real Catalysts: Importance of the Material Gap in the Rational Design of Pd Catalysts for Methane Oxidation." *ChemCatChem* 9, 1594-1600, 2017.
- 7. Q. Yuan, H. A. Doan, L. C. Grabow, S. R. Brankovic, "Finite Size Effects in Sub-monolayer Catalysts Investigated by CO Electrosorption on Pt/Pd(100)." *Journal of the American Chemical Society* 139, 13676-13679, 2017.
- 8. S. Pellizzeri, I. A. Jones, H. A. Doan, R. Q. Snurr, R. B. Getman, "Using Gas-Phase Clusters to Screen Porphyrin-supported Nanocluster Catalysts for Ethane Oxidation to Ethanol." *Catalysis Letters* 146, 2566-2573, 2016.
- 9. H-V Tran, H. A. Doan, B. D. Chandler, L. C. Grabow, "Water-assisted Oxygen Activation during Selective Oxidation Reactions." *Current Opinion in Chemical Engineering* 13, 100-108, 2016.
- 10. L. C. Grabow, Q. Yuan, H. A. Doan, S. R. Brankovic, "Novel 2D RuPt Core-Edge Nanocluster Catalyst for CO Electro-oxidation." *Surface Science* 640, 50-58, 2015.
- 11. J. Saavedra, H. A. Doan, C. J. Pursell, L. C. Grabow, B. D. Chandler, "The Critical Role of Water at the Gold-Titania Interface in Catalytic CO Oxidation." *Science* 345, 1599-1602, 2014.
 - Highlight article: G. M. Mullen, C. B. Mullins, "Water's place in Au catalysis." Science. 345, 1564-1565, 2014.
- 12. B. D. Chandler, S. Kendell, H. Doan, R. Korkosz, L. C. Grabow, C. J. Pursell, "NaBr Poisoning of Au/TiO₂ Catalysts: Effects on Kinetics, Poisoning Mechanism, and Estimation of the Number of Catalytic Active Sites." *ACS Catalysis* 2, 684-694, 2012.